<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>oVirt</title>
  <subtitle>Tag: Fosdem</subtitle>
  <id>http://ovirt.org/blog/</id>
  <link href="http://ovirt.org/blog/"/>
  <link href="http://ovirt.org/blog/tag/fosdem.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2019-05-27T15:35:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name/>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>2018 FOSDEM &amp; DEVCONF Events - Call for Proposals</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://ovirt.org/blog/2017/10/come-to-fosdem-event.html"/>
    <id>http://ovirt.org/blog/2017/10/come-to-fosdem-event.html</id>
    <published>2017-10-19T11:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-06-16T09:04:04+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>jmarks, pkliczew</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On behalf of oVirt and the Xen Project, we are excited to announce that the call for proposals is now open for the &lt;strong&gt;Virtualization &amp;amp; IaaS devroom&lt;/strong&gt; at the
upcoming &lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2018/"&gt;FOSDEM 2018&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year will mark FOSDEM’s 18th anniversary as one of the longest-running free and open source software developer events, attracting thousands of
developers and users from all over the world. FOSDEM will take place in Brussels, Belgium, February 3 &amp;amp; 4, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also coming up is &lt;a href="https://devconf.cz/cz/2018/index.html"&gt;DEVCOM&lt;/a&gt;, The 10th annual, free community conference for developers, admins, and users of free and open source Linux, JBoss technologies. DEVCONF will take place in Brno, Czech Republic, January 26-28, 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" width="176" height="47" src="/images/blog/FOSDEM_logo.png?1560777613" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="about-fosdem"&gt;About FOSDEM&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Virtualization &amp;amp; IaaS devroom at FOSDEM is a collaborative effort, organized by dedicated folks from projects such as OpenStack, Xen Project,, oVirt, QEMU, and
Foreman. Featured sessions will include topics such as open source hypervisors and virtual machine managers such as Xen Project, KVM,bhyve, and VirtualBox, and Infrastructure-as-a-Service projects such as Apache CloudStack, OpenStack, oVirt, QEMU, OpenNebula, and Ganeti.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This devroom will host presentations that focus on topics of shared interest, such as KVM; libvirt; shared storage; virtualized networking;
cloud security; clustering and high availability; interfacing with multiple hypervisors; hyperconverged deployments; and scaling across hundreds or
thousands of servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presentations will be aimed at developers working on these platforms who are looking to collaborate and improve shared infrastructure
or solve common problems. We seek topics that encourage dialog between projects and continued work post-FOSDEM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="submit-your-proposal"&gt;Submit Your Proposal&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All submissions must be made via the Pentabarf &lt;a href="https://penta.fosdem.org/submission/FOSDEM18"&gt;event planning site&lt;/a&gt;. If you have not used Pentabarf before, you will need to create an account. If you submitted proposals for FOSDEM in previous years, you can use your existing account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After creating the account, select Create Event to start the submission process. Make sure to select Virtualization and IaaS devroom from the Track
list. Please fill out all the required fields, and provide a meaningful abstract and description of your proposed session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="important-dates"&gt;Important Dates&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Submission deadline: 01 December 2017&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Acceptance notifications: 14 December 2017&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Final schedule announcement: 21 December 2017&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Devroom: 03 and 04 February 2018 (two days- different rooms)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="questions"&gt;Questions?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions about this devroom, please send your questions to our &lt;a href="https://lists.fosdem.org/listinfo/fosdem"&gt;devroom mailing list&lt;/a&gt;. You can also subscribe to the list to receive updates about important dates, session announcements, and to connect with other attendees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you all at FOSDEM!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" width="260" height="48" src="/images/blog/DEVCONF_logo.png?1560777613" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="about-denconf"&gt;About DENCONF&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DEVCONF, the 10th annual, free community conference for developers, admins, and users of free and open source Linux, JBoss technologies, will take place in the beautiful Faculty of Information Technology, Brno University of Technology, Brno, January 26-28, 2018.
&lt;a href="https://devconf.cz/cz/2018/index.html"&gt;Learn more&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="call-for-proposals"&gt;Call for Proposals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to give a talk or a workshop, run a booth or organize a community meet up at the DEVCONF? Call for proposals is now open. You can &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/forms/d/e/1FAIpQLSdrsnvIAD03oRTDwV3G7tYs8OvZZl_eHSFw5tHcCAPLn5fwjw/viewform"&gt;submit your proposal here&lt;/a&gt;. The call for proposals closes on November 17, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Call For Proposals&amp;mdash;FOSDEM 2017 Virtualization &amp; IaaS DevRoom</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://ovirt.org/blog/2016/10/call-for-proposal-fosdem-2017.html"/>
    <id>http://ovirt.org/blog/2016/10/call-for-proposal-fosdem-2017.html</id>
    <published>2016-10-13T10:45:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-06-16T09:04:04+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Proffitt</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="FOSDEM logo" width="126" height="124" src="/images/fosdem.png?1560777613" /&gt; I am excited to announce that the call for proposals is now open for the Virtualization &amp;amp; IaaS devroom at the upcoming &lt;a href="https://fosdem.org/2017/"&gt;FOSDEM 2017&lt;/a&gt;, to be hosted on February 4, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This year will mark FOSDEM’s 17th anniversary as one of the longest-running free and open source software developer events, attracting thousands of developers and users from all over the world. FOSDEM will be held once again in Brussels, Belgium, on February 4 &amp;amp; 5, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This devroom is a collaborative effort, and is organized by dedicated folks from projects such as OpenStack, Xen Project, Mesos, oVirt, QEMU, and Foreman. We would like to invite all those who are involved in these fields to submit your proposals by November 18th, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="about-the-devroom"&gt;About the Devroom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Virtualization &amp;amp; IaaS devroom will feature session topics such as open source hypervisors and virtual machine managers such as Xen Project, KVM, QEMU, bhyve, and VirtualBox, and Infrastructure-as-a-Service projects such as Apache CloudStack, OpenStack, oVirt, OpenNebula, and Ganeti.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This devroom will host presentations that focus on topics of shared interest, such as KVM; libvirt; shared storage; virtualized networking; cloud security; clustering and high availability; interfacing with multiple hypervisors; hyperconverged deployments; and scaling across hundreds or thousands of servers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presentations in this devroom will be aimed at developers working on these platforms who are looking to collaborate and improve shared infrastructure or solve common problems. We seek topics that encourage dialog between projects and continued work post-FOSDEM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="important-dates"&gt;Important Dates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Submission deadline:&lt;/strong&gt; 18 November 2016&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Acceptance notifications:&lt;/strong&gt; 04 December 2016&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Final schedule announcement:&lt;/strong&gt; 11 December 2016&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Devroom:&lt;/strong&gt; 04 February 2017 (one day)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="submit-your-proposal"&gt;Submit Your Proposal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All submissions must be made via the &lt;a href="https://penta.fosdem.org/submission/FOSDEM17"&gt;Pentabarf event planning site&lt;/a&gt;. If you have not used Pentabarf before, you will need to create an account. If you submitted proposals for FOSDEM in previous years, you can use your existing account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After creating the account, select &lt;strong&gt;Create Event&lt;/strong&gt; to start the submission process. Make sure to select &lt;strong&gt;Virtualisation and IaaS devroom&lt;/strong&gt; from the Track list. Please fill out all the required fields, and provide a meaningful abstract and description of your proposed session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="submission-guidelines"&gt;Submission Guidelines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We expect more proposals than we can possibly accept, so it is vitally important that you submit your proposal on or before the deadline. Late submissions are unlikely to be considered.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All presentation slots are 45 minutes, with 35 minutes planned for presentations, and 10 minutes for Q&amp;amp;A.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;All presentations &lt;strong&gt;will&lt;/strong&gt; be recorded and made available under Creative Commons licenses. In the &lt;em&gt;Submission notes&lt;/em&gt; field, please indicate that you agree that your presentation will be licensed under the CC-By-SA-4.0 or CC-By-4.0 license and that you agree to have your presentation recorded. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;"If my presentation is accepted for FOSDEM, I hereby agree to license all recordings, slides, and other associated materials under the Creative Commons Attribution Share-Alike 4.0 International License. Sincerely, &amp;lt;NAME&amp;gt;."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In the &lt;em&gt;Submission notes&lt;/em&gt; field, please also confirm that if your talk is accepted, you &lt;strong&gt;will&lt;/strong&gt; be able to attend FOSDEM and deliver your presentation. We will not consider proposals from prospective speakers who are unsure whether they will be able to secure funds for travel and lodging to attend FOSDEM. (Sadly, we are not able to offer travel funding for prospective speakers.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id="speaker-mentoring-program"&gt;Speaker Mentoring Program&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a part of the rising efforts to grow our communities and encourage a diverse and inclusive conference ecosystem, we're happy to announce that we'll be offering mentoring for new speakers. Our mentors can help you with tasks such as reviewing your abstract, reviewing your presentation outline or slides, or practicing your talk with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may apply to the mentoring program as a newcomer speaker if you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Never presented before or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Presented only lightning talks or&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Presented full-length talks at small meetups (&amp;lt;50 ppl)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id="submission-guidelines-1"&gt;Submission Guidelines&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mentored presentations will have 25-minute slots, where 20 minutes will include the presentation and 5 minutes will be reserved for questions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The number of newcomer session slots is limited, so we will probably not be able to accept all applications.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You must submit your talk and abstract to apply for the mentoring program, our mentors are volunteering their time and will happily provide feedback but won't write your presentation for you!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are experiencing problems with Pentabarf, the proposal submission interface, or have other questions, you can email our &lt;a href="&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#105;&amp;#097;&amp;#097;&amp;#115;&amp;#045;&amp;#118;&amp;#105;&amp;#114;&amp;#116;&amp;#045;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#118;&amp;#114;&amp;#111;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#064;&amp;#108;&amp;#105;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#115;&amp;#046;&amp;#102;&amp;#111;&amp;#115;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#109;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;"&gt;devroom mailing list&lt;/a&gt; and we will try to help you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="how-to-apply"&gt;How to Apply&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to agreeing to video recording and confirming that you can attend FOSDEM in case your session is accepted, please write "speaker mentoring program application" in the "Submission notes" field, and list any prior speaking experience or other relevant information for your application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id="call-for-mentors"&gt;Call for Mentors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interested in mentoring newcomer speakers? We'd love to have your help! Please email iaas-virt-devroom at lists.fosdem.org with a short speaker biography and any specific fields of expertise (for example, KVM, OpenStack, storage, etc.) so that we can match you with a newcomer speaker from a similar field. Estimated time investment can be as low as a 5-10 hours in total, usually distributed weekly or bi-weekly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Never mentored a newcomer speaker but interested to try? As the mentoring program coordinator, I will be happy to answer your questions and give you tips on how to optimize the mentoring process. &lt;a href="&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#098;&amp;#107;&amp;#112;&amp;#064;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#100;&amp;#104;&amp;#097;&amp;#116;&amp;#046;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;"&gt;Email me&lt;/a&gt; and I'll be happy to answer your questions!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="code-of-conduct"&gt;Code of Conduct&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the release of the updated &lt;a href="https://www.fosdem.org/2017/practical/conduct/"&gt;code of conduct for FOSDEM&lt;/a&gt;, we'd like to remind all speakers and attendees that all of the presentations and discussions in our devroom are held under the guidelines set in the CoC and we expect attendees, speakers, and volunteers to follow the CoC at all times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you submit a proposal and it is accepted, you will be required to confirm that you accept the FOSDEM CoC. If you have any questions about the CoC or wish to have one of the devroom organizers review your presentation slides or any other content for CoC compliance, please email &lt;a href="&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#105;&amp;#097;&amp;#097;&amp;#115;&amp;#045;&amp;#118;&amp;#105;&amp;#114;&amp;#116;&amp;#045;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#118;&amp;#114;&amp;#111;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#064;&amp;#108;&amp;#105;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#115;&amp;#046;&amp;#102;&amp;#111;&amp;#115;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#109;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;"&gt;us&lt;/a&gt; and we will do our best to assist you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="call-for-volunteers"&gt;Call for Volunteers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are also looking for volunteers to help run the devroom. We need assistance watching time for the speakers, and helping with video for the devroom. Please contact me, &lt;a href="&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#098;&amp;#107;&amp;#112;&amp;#064;&amp;#114;&amp;#101;&amp;#100;&amp;#104;&amp;#097;&amp;#116;&amp;#046;&amp;#099;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;"&gt;Brian Proffitt&lt;/a&gt;, for more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="questions"&gt;Questions?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions about this devroom, please send your questions to our &lt;a href="&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#105;&amp;#097;&amp;#097;&amp;#115;&amp;#045;&amp;#118;&amp;#105;&amp;#114;&amp;#116;&amp;#045;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#118;&amp;#114;&amp;#111;&amp;#111;&amp;#109;&amp;#064;&amp;#108;&amp;#105;&amp;#115;&amp;#116;&amp;#115;&amp;#046;&amp;#102;&amp;#111;&amp;#115;&amp;#100;&amp;#101;&amp;#109;&amp;#046;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#103;"&gt;devroom mailing list&lt;/a&gt;. You can also subscribe to the list to receive updates about important dates, session announcements, and to connect with other attendees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See you all at FOSDEM!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
