<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>oVirt</title>
  <subtitle>Tag: Sub Project</subtitle>
  <id>http://ovirt.org/blog/</id>
  <link href="http://ovirt.org/blog/"/>
  <link href="http://ovirt.org/blog/tag/sub-project.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2019-05-27T15:35:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name/>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Announcing the oVirt Engine DR Sub-project</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://ovirt.org/blog/2016/07/announcing-the-ovirt-engine-dr-subproject.html"/>
    <id>http://ovirt.org/blog/2016/07/announcing-the-ovirt-engine-dr-subproject.html</id>
    <published>2016-07-20T16:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-06-16T09:04:04+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Proffitt</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The oVirt Project is pleased to announce a new sub-project within the oVirt community: oVirt Engine DR, which uses the oVirt API and perform tasks that would normally require manual intervention, in case of the need for Disaster Recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, the oVirt Engine DR is a web application that uses Java, the oVirt API, PostgreSQL, and MariaDB to perform the tasks needed in a Disaster Recovery scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Features will include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Disables Power Management for Hosts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Manual Fence all Hosts in non_responsive state&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Modifies Server Storage Connections (currently directly to Engine Database)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Activates some Hosts to be able to recover from Disaster&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stores the configuration on a MariaDB database&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enables the administrator to create other users who can't change configuration but can start the procedure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;oVirt Engine DR currently exists as an independent open source project hosted on &lt;a href="https://github.com/xandradx/ovirt-engine-disaster-recovery"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt;. The project, which is currently in incubation status, includes as the owner and initial maintainers: José Eduardo Andrade Escobar, Jorge Luis Andrade Escobar, and Luis Armando Pérez Marín.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href="/develop/projects/proposals/ovirt-engine-disaster-recovery/"&gt;sub-project page&lt;/a&gt; will gather input on whether oVirt Engine DR should become a full oVirt sub-project and, if so, how best to integrate it into the oVirt stack.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
